<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="the-prism-lab.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="the-prism-lab.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-07-21T09:13:01+00:00</updated><id>the-prism-lab.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>A simple, whitespace theme for academics. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Organic chemistry is nothing but pattern recognition!?</title><link href="the-prism-lab.github.io/blog/2024/org-pattern/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Organic chemistry is nothing but pattern recognition!?"/><published>2024-02-01T13:56:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-02-01T13:56:00+00:00</updated><id>the-prism-lab.github.io/blog/2024/org-pattern</id><content type="html" xml:base="the-prism-lab.github.io/blog/2024/org-pattern/"><![CDATA[<p>“This is nothing but pattern recognition!” As unsettling as that might sound to many organic chemistry practitioners, it’s a comment one of my former supervisors made about (undergraduate) organic chemistry. Years later, this remark resurfaced as I dived into the world of machine learning.</p> <p>I vividly remember a brilliant college classmate’s strong interest in neuroscience. Being more physics- and math-minded, I didn’t quite grasp it then. It wasn’t until recently that I realized how the process of receiving information, forming memories, or making decisions could be mathematically modeled as communications between neural networks. (Huge thanks to Fei-Fei Li’s inspiring memoir, <em><a href="https://www.amazon.co.uk/Worlds-See-Curiosity-Exploration-Discovery/dp/1250897939">The Worlds I See</a></em>—highly recommended!)</p> <p>The basic unit (algorithm) in these neural networks, aptly named a perceptron, takes input (electrical) signals and performs binary classifications. It mimics what an actual neuron does: receiving signals, accumulating and modulating them, and firing an output signal only when the total strength of inputs exceeds a certain threshold. While complex cognitive activities involve large neural networks, at the most fundamental level, whether it’s a single neuron or a single perceptron, the primary task is classification.</p> <p>Classification is indeed how we learn about the world. As babies, we learn to identify a cat versus a toy, or what’s edible versus inedible. As we grow older, we categorize words into nouns and verbs and recognize facial and vocal expressions that signify emotions like happiness or anger. We make sense of the world by organizing and classifying information, which is essential for understanding, decision-making, and communication.</p> <p>Humans are amazingly good at classification. It allows us to identify risks in a split second and avoid accidents; it even enables us to sense our surroundings without direct attention. However, this ability is so deeply ingrained that it can lead to unconscious biases, such as distinguishing people who look different from us and isolating us from embracing diversity.</p> <p>Returning to chemistry: recognizing that our learning and cognitive processes begin with classification makes the idea that “organic chemistry is nothing but pattern recognition” seem less outrageous. However, going from classification to true pattern recognition involves additional tasks like feature identification/extraction and regression. These might include understanding/evaluating electrophilicity strength, reaction site crowdedness, temperature values, or environmental polarity. Admittedly, these subtleties may not be fully grasped even by most seasoned chemists, but they can be effectively learned by machines given suitable data sets, as evidenced by the growing number of publications on the application of <a href="https://scholar.google.co.uk/scholar?q=synthetic+organic+chemistry+artificial+intelligence+review+&amp;hl=en&amp;as_sdt=0,5&amp;as_rr=1">artificial intelligence in synthetic organic chemistry</a>.</p> <p>To conclude, let me quote Flynn and Ogilvie from <a href="https://pubs.acs.org/doi/10.1021/ed500284d">their article</a> in the <em>Journal of Chemical Education</em>: “Chemical reactions follow patterns, and these patterns can allow a chemist to predict how a chemical will behave, even if they have never seen a particular reaction before.” Since we’re not ditching learning, teaching, or using electron-pushing formalism in our minds anytime soon, we might improve our approach to thinking about and practicing organic chemistry by comparing methods that fundamentally make machines “smarter” in synthesis.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="AI"/><category term="learning"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Organic chemistry through the lens of machine learning and human cognition]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Decoding “struggle” — my observations</title><link href="the-prism-lab.github.io/blog/2023/struggle/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Decoding “struggle” — my observations"/><published>2023-12-01T13:56:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-12-01T13:56:00+00:00</updated><id>the-prism-lab.github.io/blog/2023/struggle</id><content type="html" xml:base="the-prism-lab.github.io/blog/2023/struggle/"><![CDATA[<p>A word I found very frequently in student emails is <strong>struggle</strong>. Instead of employing alternative expressions like <em>be stuck</em>, <em>have a hard time</em>, <em>have trouble</em>, or <em>have difficulty</em>, they consistently lean towards using <em>struggle</em>. This linguistic divergence presents a cultural contrast for me after relocating to the UK, as I tend to associate <em>struggle</em> with more serious connotations</p> <p>This observation prompted me to reflect, and I realized it might largely be a regional word preference. A cursory exploration of the verb forms of <em>struggle</em> in The Corpus of Global Web-Based English (<a href="https://www.english-corpora.org/glowbe/">GloWbE</a>) confirms not only a higher frequency of use but also a markedly greater overall occurrence of this word in GB compared to any other country in the database (Figure 1).</p> <div class="row my-4"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0 text-center"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/GloWbe_struggle_v-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/GloWbe_struggle_v-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/GloWbe_struggle_v-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/GloWbe_struggle_v.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1 mx-auto d-block" width="756" height="156" alt="Comparison of the word STRUGGLE used in various countries" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> <figcaption class="caption"><p><strong>Figure 1</strong>. Comparison of the word STRUGGLE used in various countries. In each box, the upper number is the occurrence, and the lower number is the frequency in per million. Data retrieved from GloWbE through www.english-corpora.org.</p> </figcaption> </figure> </div> </div> <p>Yet, delving into the historical trajectory of this term reveals a notable surge in popularity around the year 2000 in both British and American books, according to the <a href="https://books.google.com/ngrams/">Google Books Ngram Viewer</a> (Figure 2a). The nearly identical trends observed here may suggest a universal phenomenon across most English-speaking countries. Intriguingly, examining the noun and verb forms of <em>struggle</em> shows distinct patterns (Figure 2b). The noun usage gained traction as early as 1840, consistently surpassing that of the verb form for over a century.</p> <p>Curiously, around 2000, the verb form began to be employed frequently to signify “making strenuous or violent efforts in the face of difficulties or opposition” or “proceeding with difficulty or great effort,” according to <a href="https://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/struggle">Merriam-Webster</a>. The rapid growth in the usage of the verb form is noteworthy, surpassing the noun form in frequency after 2010. In fact, there appears to be a recent decreasing trend in the use of <em>struggle</em> as a noun.</p> <p>Since the Google Books Ngram Viewer only provides data up to 2019, a comparison using other text corpora, such as <a href="https://www.english-corpora.org/now/">NOW</a> (News on the Web, 2010–present) and <a href="https://www.english-corpora.org/coca/">COCA</a> (Corpus of Contemporary American English, 1990–2019), has been included to depict the evolving trends in usage. I should note that the scale of the year axis is not linear, allowing for a clearer representation of trends in recent years.</p> <div class="row my-4"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0 text-center"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/Trend_struggle2-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/Trend_struggle2-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/Trend_struggle2-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/Trend_struggle2.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1 mx-auto d-block" width="516" height="549" alt="Trends of STRUGGLE verb/noun usage" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> <figcaption class="caption"><p><strong>Figure 2</strong>. (a) Comparison of the trend of STRUGGLE used as a verb in British and American English. Data retrieved from Books Ngram Viewer (books.google.com/ngrams). (b) The trend of STRUGGLE used retrieved from Books Ngram Viewer, COCA, and NOW corpora through www.english-corpora.org.</p> </figcaption> </figure> </div> </div> <p>The question arises: What caused the rapidly increased use of <em>struggle</em> as a verb? At this stage, I do not want to make any suggestions but simply want to share this observation. How would you interpret this data? Does it suggest that life has become more difficult than it was 20 years ago? While I hesitate to draw such conclusions, I sincerely hope that the current upward trend in the use of <em>struggle</em> will subside in the near future.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="society"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Regional and historical trends in using struggle as a verb]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Exploring thionation with Hückel molecular orbital theory</title><link href="the-prism-lab.github.io/blog/2023/thio-Huckel/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Exploring thionation with Hückel molecular orbital theory"/><published>2023-02-01T13:56:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-02-01T13:56:00+00:00</updated><id>the-prism-lab.github.io/blog/2023/thio-Huckel</id><content type="html" xml:base="the-prism-lab.github.io/blog/2023/thio-Huckel/"><![CDATA[<p>Hückel Molecular Orbital (HMO) theory stands as one of my favourite concepts from my undergraduate studies in physical organic chemistry. Despite its simplicity and the underlying assumptions, it offers an intuitive understanding of π-conjugated molecules and is a readily comprehensible extension of the somewhat simplistic particle-in-a-box model.</p> <p>Recently, while pondering the question of why thionating a carbonyl molecule enhances its electron-accepting capabilities, as explored in our 2023 publication (PCCP <a href="https://pubs.rsc.org/en/content/articlelanding/2023/cp/d2cp05186a">DOI: 10.1039/D2CP05186A</a>), I realized that the good old HMO theory could offer a fairly satisfying explanation. This question arose from our observations while working with various thiocarbonyl molecules (R<sub>2</sub>C=S). We (as well as others) consistently observed that these molecules exhibit a greater propensity to accept electrons than their carbonyl counterparts (R<sub>2</sub>C=O). This observation appeared to defy expectations based on a somewhat simplistic consideration of electronegativity (2.58 for sulfur and 3.44 for oxygen).</p> <p>Upon closer analysis, we revealed that the enhanced electron affinity in the C=O $\rightarrow$ C=S substitution stems from the weaker overlap between sulfur’s 3p orbitals and carbon’s 2p orbitals in C=S, in comparison to the better interactions between the valence 2p orbitals of carbon and oxygen in C=O. This reduced overlap results in a less effective antibonding interaction, leading to a lower LUMO energy and increased electron affinity.</p> <p>The diminished overlap between (2p)<sub>C</sub> and (3p)<sub>S</sub> is well-represented by the (empirical) parameters utilized in the HMO theory. In the HMO Hamiltonian matrix, the Coulomb integral <em>α</em><sub>C</sub> represents the energy of the individual (2p<sub>π</sub>)<sub>C</sub> atomic orbital of carbon, while the resonance integral <em>β</em><sub>CC</sub> characterizes the coupling between adjacent (2p<sub>π</sub>)<sub>C</sub> orbitals. By adjusting the integral values for carbon through <em>α</em><sub>X</sub> = <em>α</em><sub>C</sub> + <em>k</em><sub>X</sub> × <em>β</em><sub>CC</sub> and <em>β</em><sub>XY</sub> = <em>k</em><sub>XY</sub> × <em>β</em><sub>CC</sub>, the property of the frontier orbitals of heteroatom-containing π systems can be estimated in the Hückel framework (<em>k</em><sub>X</sub> and <em>k</em><sub>XY</sub> are proportionality constants for heteroatom X).</p> <p>Using formaldehyde (H<sub>2</sub>CO) and thioformaldehyde (H<sub>2</sub>CS) as examples, we have:</p> <p><em>α</em><sub>O</sub> = <em>α</em><sub>C</sub> + <em>k</em><sub>O</sub> × <em>β</em><sub>CC</sub> = <em>α</em><sub>C</sub> + 0.97<em>β</em><sub>CC</sub><br/> <em>β</em><sub>C=O</sub> = <em>k</em><sub>C=O</sub> × <em>β</em><sub>CC</sub> = 1.06<em>β</em><sub>CC</sub></p> <p>and</p> <p><em>α</em><sub>S</sub> = <em>α</em><sub>C</sub> + <em>k</em><sub>S</sub> × <em>β</em><sub>CC</sub> = <em>α</em><sub>C</sub> + 0.46<em>β</em><sub>CC</sub><br/> <em>β</em><sub>C=S</sub> = <em>k</em><sub>C=S</sub> × <em>β</em><sub>CC</sub> = 0.81<em>β</em><sub>CC</sub></p> <p>The energy of the π* level would be:</p> <p><em>E</em>(π*) = <em>α</em><sub>C</sub> – 0.68<em>β</em><sub>CC</sub> for H<sub>2</sub>CO<br/> <em>E</em>(π*) = <em>α</em><sub>C</sub> – 0.61<em>β</em><sub>CC</sub> for H<sub>2</sub>CS</p> <p>i.e., <strong>the π* level of H<sub>2</sub>CS is less destabilized</strong>.</p> <p>Even without solving the eigenvalue problem of HMO theory, this result is intuitively expected: the resonance integral β<em><sub>C=S</sub> is smaller than β</em><sub>C=O</sub>, lowering the energy of the π* orbital in H<sub>2</sub>CS. In our PCCP paper, we further showed that this <em>β</em><sub>C=X</sub> can be <strong>quantitatively estimated</strong> as <em>β</em><sub>C=X</sub> ≈ |⟨<em>h</em><sub>C</sub>|<strong>F</strong>|<em>h</em><sub>S</sub>⟩|, where <em>h</em><sub>X</sub> are natural atomic hybrid orbitals (NHO), and <strong>F</strong> is the Fock (Kohn–Sham) operator.</p> <p>However, it is important to note that semiempirical HMO may not always yield the correct picture. When comparing ester (RC(O)OR) and thioester (RC(O)SR), we found that <em>E</em>(π*) = <em>α</em><sub>C</sub> – 0.79<em>β</em><sub>CC</sub> for the former and <em>α</em><sub>C</sub> – 0.86<em>β</em><sub>CC</sub> for the latter, suggesting a higher π* level for the sulfur compound. This result, however, conflicts with DFT calculations and the experimental reduction potentials of these molecules. The inconsistency arises from the <em>larger</em> <em>β</em><sub>C–S</sub> = 0.69<em>β</em><sub>CC</sub> than <em>β</em><sub>C–O</sub> = 0.66<em>β</em><sub>CC</sub> (as opposed to being <em>smaller</em> in the previous comparison; note the difference in <em>β</em><sub>C=X</sub> and <em>β</em><sub>C–X</sub> used here). Therefore, despite the elegance of HMO, we recommend using the DFT-based NBO/NHO analysis to obtain a more reliable understanding of the electronic effects of heteroatom substitution on π*-conjugated molecules. Please see <a href="https://pubs.rsc.org/en/content/articlelanding/2023/cp/d2cp05186a">DOI: 10.1039/D2CP05186A</a> for detailed discussion.</p> <p>For this work, we also prepared a (yet another!? <a href="https://pubs.acs.org/doi/full/10.1021/acs.jchemed.8b00244">link1</a> and <a href="http://www.hulis.free.fr/">link 2</a>) Python script to <a href="https://colab.research.google.com/drive/1BE0aXDqAEAWV_42iadY7pkE6J79Moa-N?usp=sharing">solve simple Hückel systems</a> (not the ‘extended Hückel’). While this script is primarily designed for π-conjugated hydrocarbons, you can adapt it for heteroatom-containing systems by adjusting the Coulomb and resonance integrals in the Hückel matrix. Several examples are included in this interactive Jupyter Notebook for your reference (hosted in <a href="https://colab.google/">Google Colab</a>).</p> <p>Furthermore, to enhance usability, the script can generate the Hückel matrix from a molecular SMILES string using the RDKit toolkit’s <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">GetAdjacencyMatrix</code> module. To end this post: You may find it intriguing to explore this script and compare the energy levels of two isomeric molecules: 2-phenyl-1,3-butadiene: <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">C=CC(c1ccccc1)=C</code> and 1,4-divinylbenzene: <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">C=Cc1ccc(cc1)C=C</code> (spoiler alert: they are the same!).</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="calculations"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Hückel theory reveals sulfur's electron-accepting secret]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Bürgi–Dunitz angle revisited</title><link href="the-prism-lab.github.io/blog/2019/BD-angle/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Bürgi–Dunitz angle revisited"/><published>2019-08-01T13:56:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-08-01T13:56:00+00:00</updated><id>the-prism-lab.github.io/blog/2019/BD-angle</id><content type="html" xml:base="the-prism-lab.github.io/blog/2019/BD-angle/"><![CDATA[<p>I recently came across <a href="https://www.ch.imperial.ac.uk/rzepa/blog/?p=14016">Prof. Rzepa’s blog post</a> on the Bürgi–Dunitz angle—a topic very close to my heart. Embarrassingly, I didn’t know about this concept until halfway through my PhD at ETH, despite regular interactions with Prof. Dunitz himself!</p> <p>The discovery of the Bürgi–Dunitz angle marked one of the key moments in crystallography, organic and supramolecular chemistry, and molecular orbital analysis. I was very impressed by the beauty and neat idea behind this study, and I’ve often used it as an example to show students the vast information that can be gleaned from structural analysis. It was truly insightful how Bürgi and Dunitz were able to <a href="https://pubs.acs.org/doi/10.1021/ja00796a058">distill the preferred reaction trajectory from just 6 (!) crystal structures</a>.</p> <p>Nearly 50 years later, with over a million structures now in the CCDC database, we should be much better equipped to re-validate the theory behind the Bürgi–Dunitz angle through extensive structural analysis. However, if you look at the angle of any nucleophilic atom (N, O, S, etc.) approaching carbonyl functionalities, the most commonly found angles are actually around 90º, not near 105º, as <a href="https://www.ch.imperial.ac.uk/rzepa/blog/?p=14016">Prof. Rzepa clearly demonstrated</a>. So, were Bürgi and Dunitz wrong?</p> <p>After a close examination of the structural hits, I realized the primary source of this discrepancy comes from the overwhelming number of structures featuring <a href="https://scripts.iucr.org/cgi-bin/paper?ha0167"><em>antiparallel C=O interactions</em></a>. In these cases, the oxygen of one moiety sits on the carbon of another, resulting in an O…C=O angle of approximately 90º. This is quite fascinating; starting from an analysis of nucleophilic addition to a carbonyl group, we ended up uncovering one of the most prevalent non-covalent interactions in proteins!</p> <p>I’ve already added my comment below Prof. Rzepa’s post. Part of the reason I wanted to write about this again here is to emphasize a crucial point: in the age of machine learning, it’s incredibly easy to gather vast amounts of data. Yet, it remains extremely challenging to discern the actual information or patterns within that data. After all, as ML practitioners often say: “Your model will be only as good (or as bad) as the data you have.”</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="interactions"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Big data shows a twist, highlighting how tricky it is to interpret big datasets]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Goodbye Northwestern, it has been a wonderful time</title><link href="the-prism-lab.github.io/blog/2018/bye-NU/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Goodbye Northwestern, it has been a wonderful time"/><published>2018-11-01T13:56:00+00:00</published><updated>2018-11-01T13:56:00+00:00</updated><id>the-prism-lab.github.io/blog/2018/bye-NU</id><content type="html" xml:base="the-prism-lab.github.io/blog/2018/bye-NU/"><![CDATA[<div class="float-left" style="width: 250; margin-right: 25px;"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/APPLE-Virtual-Reward-1-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/APPLE-Virtual-Reward-1-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/APPLE-Virtual-Reward-1-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/APPLE-Virtual-Reward-1.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="250" height="auto" alt="Northwestern University Hood" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <p>After a long period of job searching, I am delighted to share that I will be taking up a new post at Cardiff University, starting from January 2019. I am deeply indebted to all my mentors, colleagues, friends, and family for their unwavering help and support throughout this process.</p> <p>My past six and a half years at Northwestern, focusing on photoenergy research, have been a truly wonderful experience. It was a genuine privilege to collaborate daily with some of the brightest minds (you know who you are!) and to have access to cutting-edge technologies. My perspectives on science and its interplay with education and society have grown and matured significantly during this time. These insights are truly the best gift I will carry with me across the Atlantic Ocean and eagerly pass on to my future coworkers.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="move"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Judging at Intel ISEF 2017</title><link href="the-prism-lab.github.io/blog/2017/ISEF2017/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Judging at Intel ISEF 2017"/><published>2017-06-01T13:56:00+00:00</published><updated>2017-06-01T13:56:00+00:00</updated><id>the-prism-lab.github.io/blog/2017/ISEF2017</id><content type="html" xml:base="the-prism-lab.github.io/blog/2017/ISEF2017/"><![CDATA[<div class="float-right" style="width: 200px; margin-left: 25px;"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/isef17-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/isef17-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/isef17-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/isef17.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="200" height="auto" alt="ISEF17" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <p>“Science’s rightful place is in service of society” (D. Sarewitz, 2013) has always been a core belief of mine. This past summer, I was incredibly fortunate to participate as a Chemistry Grand Awards judge at the International Science and Engineering Fair (ISEF), the world’s largest pre-college science competition.</p> <p>Although science fairs were a significant part of my high school experience, I never quite reached the heights of many of my classmates. ISEF 2017 was my first time seeing such a high-level competition, and I was genuinely impressed by:</p> <ul> <li>One high schooler’s perseverance in identifying an undocumented ferric sulfate compound, derived from the reaction of sulfuric acid with gold ore he obtained from hiking.</li> <li>The applicability of an algorithm developed by another student to filter and assign signals in high-dimensional protein NMR spectroscopy, aiming to accelerate drug discovery (and by his smartness, too!).</li> <li>The usefulness of silk fibers as moisture-activated torsional actuators, a discovery by yet another student.</li> <li>And many, many other inspiring projects.</li> </ul> <p>The judges’ caucus was another unique experience. Our group consisted of industrial scientists, university professors, researchers, postdocs, and PhD students. Some had far more science fair judging experience than others. We thoroughly discussed <strong>all(!)</strong> the projects, trying to persuade our colleagues why one project deserved to be ranked higher or lower. The voting and discussion cycle repeated again and again until all the prizes were ultimately decided. (Students who received awards, you truly owe a big thank you to the eloquent and passionate judges who advocated for your projects!)</p> <p>Overall, judging ISEF was a fantastic experience, especially witnessing and feeling the pure enthusiasm for science from all the students. I’m very glad I could contribute and help. A special thanks to my grad school friend, Grace, for the invitation!</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="society"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Ethylhexyl in real life</title><link href="the-prism-lab.github.io/blog/2016/ethylhexyl/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Ethylhexyl in real life"/><published>2016-01-03T13:56:00+00:00</published><updated>2016-01-03T13:56:00+00:00</updated><id>the-prism-lab.github.io/blog/2016/ethylhexyl</id><content type="html" xml:base="the-prism-lab.github.io/blog/2016/ethylhexyl/"><![CDATA[<p>As a bit of a “purist”, I’ve always had a mild aversion to 2-ethylhexyl substituents in my molecules, as it has an undefined stereogenic center at the 2 position. Molecules incorporating such a functionality thus are random mixtures(!) of (<em>R</em>)- and (<em>S</em>)-stereoisomers, not to mention molecules possessing multiple 2-ethylhexyl substituents.</p> <p>For material scientists, particularly aromatic polymer chemists, however, 2-ethylhexyl is a go-to choice for boosting solubility, as its bulky nature effectively disrupts π-stacking and aggregation. What’s really striking is how ubiquitous 2-ethylhexyl-containing molecules are in our daily lives, far beyond the confines of research labs. It makes me wonder if their widespread use also hinges on their aggregation-modulating properties.</p> <p>Just to name a few common examples:</p> <ul> <li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cetane_improver">2-ethylhexyl nitrate (2-EHN)</a> is a crucial cetane improver for diesel fuels.</li> <li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bis(2-ethylhexyl)_phthalate">Bis(2-ethylhexyl) phthalate</a>, produced at about 3 billion kg/year, is a primary plasticizer for PVC.</li> <li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Octocrylene">Octocrylene</a> and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Octyl_methoxycinnamate">octyl methoxycinnamate</a> are key ingredients in sunscreen products, vital for absorbing UVB and UVA radiation.</li> </ul> <p>Without a doubt, I should have given 2-ethylhexyl much more credit!</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="interactions"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[From fuel to sunscreen, the quirky 2-ethylhexyl group is everywhere]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">We know so little, so little indeed, about solubility</title><link href="the-prism-lab.github.io/blog/2015/PDI_ester/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="We know so little, so little indeed, about solubility"/><published>2015-01-03T13:56:00+00:00</published><updated>2015-01-03T13:56:00+00:00</updated><id>the-prism-lab.github.io/blog/2015/PDI_ester</id><content type="html" xml:base="the-prism-lab.github.io/blog/2015/PDI_ester/"><![CDATA[<p>Perlyene diimide (PDI) is famously insoluble, and it’s a well-known belief that <strong>linear aliphatic <em>N</em>-substituents</strong> won’t do much to improve this.</p> <p>However, the Grozema group published a mind-blowing work back in 2014 (DOI: <a href="http://pubs.rsc.org/en/Content/ArticleLanding/2014/CC/c4cc00330f#!divAbstract">10.1039/c4cc00330f</a>) that completely challenged this common assumption (along with other important findings, of course).</p> <p>Take a look at the picture: by tweaking the <strong>position of the ester group</strong> (while maintaining the overall length of the substituents the same), the solubility of PDI increases from negligible to over 100 mg/mL! I’ve known about this work for a while (thanks Pat for showing me this paper), and I still struggle to fully make sense of it. This just goes to show how little we truly understand about intermolecular interactions; there’s so much more to learn!</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/pdi_ester-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/pdi_ester-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/pdi_ester-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/pdi_ester.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1 mx-auto d-block" width="400" height="auto" alt="PDI Ester Solubility Data" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> <figcaption class="caption"><p>Solubility of PDI derivatives with varying linear <em>N</em>-substituents. (Adapted from DOI: 10.1039/c4cc00330f)</p> </figcaption> </figure> </div> </div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="interactions"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A tiny tweak to linear chains makes PDI super soluble]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Alkyl groups modulate π-stacking interactions, size isn’t everything</title><link href="the-prism-lab.github.io/blog/2015/alkyl-pi/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Alkyl groups modulate π-stacking interactions, size isn’t everything"/><published>2015-01-02T13:56:00+00:00</published><updated>2015-01-02T13:56:00+00:00</updated><id>the-prism-lab.github.io/blog/2015/alkyl-pi</id><content type="html" xml:base="the-prism-lab.github.io/blog/2015/alkyl-pi/"><![CDATA[<p>The team led by Ken Shimizu at the University of South Carolina recently published a super interesting finding: the strength of attractive or repulsive forces in π-stacked aromatic molecules can be significantly influenced by their alkyl substituents.</p> <p>What’s cool is that it’s not just about the size of those alkyl groups. If the <strong>interacting surface area</strong> between the aromatic rings is large enough, even molecules with bulky <em>tert</em>-butyl (<em>t</em>Bu) groups can show stronger attraction than those with smaller methyl (Me) groups!</p> <p>Here is the link to their publication: <a href="http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1002/anie.201602752/full">http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1002/anie.201602752/full</a>0</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="interactions"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Intermolecular contact matters as much as their formal size for pi-stacking interactions]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Does methanol dissolve silica?</title><link href="the-prism-lab.github.io/blog/2015/silica/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Does methanol dissolve silica?"/><published>2015-01-01T01:01:00+00:00</published><updated>2015-01-01T01:01:00+00:00</updated><id>the-prism-lab.github.io/blog/2015/silica</id><content type="html" xml:base="the-prism-lab.github.io/blog/2015/silica/"><![CDATA[<p>This is an age-old question for people using MeOH in their flash chromatography.</p> <p>Turns out, <strong>methanol doesn’t actually dissolve silica gel.</strong> The “white stuff” you sometimes see is tiny silica particles (fines) breaking off, especially from granular silica when using DCM/MeOH gradients. Spherical silica seems better at holding its own. Have a look at an <a href="https://www.biotage.com/blog/how-much-methanol-can-i-use-with-my-silica-flash-column">interesting analysis</a> conducted by Biotage.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="labs"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[That "silica in your product" from methanol is just shedding tiny particles!]]></summary></entry></feed>